[SPEAKER_00]: So, does anyone have any ideas to start off the discussion?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, in previous talks, we looked into the Middle Way and we established that the Middle Way is the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we also said that with the acquisition of yoniso manasikāra, there comes to be the arising of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I wonder if we can take up the question, what is yoniso manasikāra, and how does one put that into practice?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are people interested in looking into this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the most, eh... fundamental directive that you could give regarding that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding yorisaṃyosikāra?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, perhaps you could start out by saying that
[SPEAKER_03]: yoniso manasikāra, we could say, you know, attending from the origin, or from the source, or through the source even, as a starting point.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I find it practically useful to approach it in terms of the direction of one's attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, ordinarily, one's attention is directed
[SPEAKER_03]: There are two objects in front of you, where things are colorful, vivid, tasty, opaque, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is where there's the main essential pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in order to see where the domain begins and ends, I find it useful to think in terms of a direction of attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, yoniso manasikāra can be described as attending in the opposite way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, everything in that direction stays, but
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything which is revealed there is possible only because there is something else which doesn't partake of that directionality, but which needs to be there in order for all those other things to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, something which needs to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, for sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't directly attend to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as well, something that will never just appear by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's it's never magically going to pop out of nowhere, based on watching things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aha, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're saying that if someone thinks that by getting absorbed into an object there, or by focusing on something there, that is not how this source or origin of attention is going to be disclosed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because you might think that
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, certainly, people feel that absorption practices
[SPEAKER_00]: Reveal something in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is something that you get to see which you didn't see before.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how you define it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be some special perceptions of what people think impermanence is, like flux is a common example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you might get visions about your body, like extraordinary visions, let's say, things that you never perceived before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is that
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if those things come up, they won't be on the level of that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're still going to be on the same level that you started from, which was absorption into the object.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if there are two paths,
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're leading in different directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't take the left path and magically end up in the same place where the right path is taking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you can't, through focusing on objects, eventually find or recognize the basis for any experience that you might have.
[SPEAKER_03]: Including that whole practice of wanting to become absorbed in objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can basically only take you further in that direction, and then, once you kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you reach a certain limit, let's say, that's beyond what you're used to, that's gonna feel special.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still on the level of content, still on the level of experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you just keep doing that for 30 years, eventually, it's not gonna be extraordinary anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll need more, and you'll need more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no end to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that's without satiation, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, what's the other thing that is fundamentally without satiation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, for sensual pleasures, that's just going to be endless.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know, if you take a more, let's say, general or even phenomenological outlook and we are discussing the directionality of attention, then all those meditation practices that are concerned with focusing on something, staying with something in front of you,
[SPEAKER_03]: All that is essentially meditation with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if the object itself might not be seen as particularly sensual, it partakes of that same directionality.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is not how you are going to see that desire for sensuality is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to have a reference point that is outside of that direction of attention, which is precisely the origin that we are now discussing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, the issue with that is...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's also the inherent dissatisfaction, like we were just saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of getting something better than what you had, but it's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Better than what you have within the same way of existing, so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not actually transforming the way that you regard your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like within the same seeking of pleasure, you find some... a pleasure that's more special than the others.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not... you... that's why exactly it's... it wouldn't... by most people, it wouldn't be seen as mutually exclusive to have the pleasure essentiality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the pleasure of meditation, at the same time, it would be seen as kind of compatible, even, because they're not really... it's not really the direction of renunciation, which is the direction that can only be achieved through recognizing that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, furthermore, that recognition, for someone who has been used to the... to live independent on objects, it should
[SPEAKER_00]: Probably feel more... not necessarily painful, but it will bring a certain amount of...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no dissonance to their experience because it's not... it's kind of destabilizing the mode of being that they're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you can... you can tell yourself if this is a type of meditation that people who are used to proliferation in the very mundane sense can easily succeed with and get good results and it's just kind of like... it just
[SPEAKER_00]: It just works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can see that it's not really... it didn't force them to actually change their mental framework, so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just took place within the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so that... that's one way that you can characterize or describe what that... or say... or talk about one of the consequences of having discerned
[SPEAKER_00]: That origin is that it forces you to change the way you live, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't just remain abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't just let you keep going in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to affect the fundamental change in your attitude, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_03]: It brings about the revaluation
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, of everything that that you are used to, where you used to go for your pleasure, how you used to avoid pain, that whole domain is now in relief against something else, which is that origin, which has now been discerned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But perhaps we should clear up that it is not a matter of just seeing this once, and then all of that framework is gonna flip around and things are done.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is something that
[SPEAKER_03]: You see, this is something that one needs to work on, but it is not that that origin or source itself is in need of development, because it's upstream of all that, but what needs to happen is that one needs to get into the habit of attending from that origin to one's experience, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, you see, the difficulty then is that
[SPEAKER_03]: From the point... You see, in that direction, there's not that much going on compared to that other direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the more one dis... disrides to speak about the discernment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is in reference to that origin that the pull of the senses becomes almost tangible.
[SPEAKER_03]: You feel that you were pulled away or that you are falling from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, before that, it was just like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even feel the pull, because you're already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already flying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is like as if somebody is floating on the river, and as long as you are floating along with the river, it might be more comfortable or less comfortable, but what you will not be able to discern is the force
[SPEAKER_03]: The current.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now suppose there's a bridge there, with a strong post or a pillar, in the middle of that river, and you decide to hold on to that post or pillar.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you do that, you don't need to go against.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just need to hold on to that post.
[SPEAKER_03]: Only then, for the first time, do you actually feel the force that was pulling you, dragging you along.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, one way in which one can practically say that one is practicing attending from the origin widely, is that, in a sense, that pool of the senses becomes much more noticeable in one's experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it is in relation to that, that one's mind then begins to develop, which raises the question, if that pool, if you now feel that pool, then what do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, what's next?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's nice to discern that origin, but practically speaking, if you want to, let's say, stay there, then there need to be a number of other things in place, that this is practically gonna have right results, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, perhaps, we can go into that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, how is now one practically going to go about it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, how are you not going to overlook that which already doesn't appear in front of you?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that also, like, as you said,
[SPEAKER_00]: Preventing yourself from going with a pull, so that gives us a chance to explain or illustrate what that origin actually would be, because from what we said now, it sounds like an abstract notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... Yeah, so, let's say there is a pull towards centrality, the most common way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, how would you go about discerning the origin and preventing yourself from falling into the natural habit, which is
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing something on account of that's neutrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like you said, the first step is to not do something on account of that pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but is that a matter of choice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraint, well, at least restraining on the bodily and verbal level, that is a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you... would you be able to not act by body and speech if you just, colloquially speaking, lose your mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just
[SPEAKER_00]: Forget and go back to the status quo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to keep to not act, even in the basic bodily sense, unless you have a sense of recognition of something else that's a background to your experience, such as your value of restraint?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I was going to say, is that even taking on restraint would kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, like, to the extent that a person wouldn't do things, like, even with, you know, without the help of the dhamma, let's say a person has some kind of ideal, some kind of overarching principle to their life, based on which they prevent themselves from committing certain actions when
[SPEAKER_00]: When they have, you know, sensual, sensual desires arising, that would require a degree of yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it could be like following the Ten Commandments or something, whatever it might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's obviously a little, and it's not enough for liberation in the in the Buddhist sense, but anybody who doesn't act out of sensuality has more, a little bit more yoniso manasikāra than the one who does, because
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you are kind of... your whole experience is pointing towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you said, it's like a river.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, if there's nothing... if there's truly nothing holding you back, or if you're not holding yourself back, there's simply no way that you won't float along with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so that's a... that's to clear up what that origin is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you say, well, it's not an... it's not an object, that can be turned into an object as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more like anything that, in a practical sense at least, for people to get started, it would be just a recognition, in the most broad... in the broadest sense, that prevents you from acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you said, there are other things that have to be in place there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like doing it once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like a person, okay, you have the desire arising, and then, I recognize, I shouldn't be acting out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thought there is, comparatively speaking, more yonison manasikāra than the person who didn't think, I shouldn't act out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, it's not a matter of just having that there once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, the pressure is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what should a person do then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but you see, perhaps one step back still.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it seems to me that it would be possible for someone to take on some basic restraint and to recognize that it is in their welfare to not act out of every random impulse or appetite that arises in their mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that still doesn't necessarily disclose the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is possible that somebody has some wish.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we might say that that is more yoniso, which I think is correct.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But still, they might be completely oblivious to the fact that there is a further discernment possible, which changes the whole overall outlook.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is not that mere restraint is in and of itself going to reveal that origin of attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's not that it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily that it has to be revealed, but just to kind of give an idea of what it is, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that counter-choice, you could call it that, not to act out, is a form of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what I was trying to get at.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if one wants to deliberately
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, yeah, so how could you...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, we could approach it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: How could you refine it so that it's no longer just a choice, a coarse choice to not do something, which pretty much anyone can do, for different motivations even?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can postpone the pleasure because you want more pleasure later.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would someone turn it into
[SPEAKER_00]: Into, like, development of this principle that would, for example, lead to the abandonment, the actual abandonment of the unwholesome mental state, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, one thing someone could do is question themselves about the nature of the sensual pleasures that are in the opposite direction of attending from the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, one is subjected to unpleasant feeling or to the possibility of unpleasant feeling and if the only thing one knows
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if the goal is to put pleasurable sense experience over against it, which is the only thing the ordinary person knows how to do in relation to the basic dukkha, then it's like one steps into the direction to gain pleasure in order to deal with the pain which is in that same direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so something painful happens there, and then ayoniso is, oh, I want to have pleasure over there,
[SPEAKER_03]: That should overrule or overpower the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what is not understood, is that as long as one steps away from that origin, into that domain there,
[SPEAKER_03]: Wanting pleasure, regardless of how refined and intense the prospect of that pleasure is, by falling away from that origin, you make yourself liable to that dukkha.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... so how this is... so how is this going to practically then be discerned more closely and practiced, is by seeing that that whole domain, whether it is pleasure or pain that is on offer,
[SPEAKER_03]: That is what one can abandon from the point of view of attending from that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, like, the pain that is involved in a sensual desire is to be recognized at that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't see that, all you're seeing is the offer of pleasure, but right there, kind of like the foundation of your whole engagement, is this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on top of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're walking on top of all that, getting all this pleasure, but the foundation is still the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could say that's a form of... an analogy for what that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the foundation for everything else in your experience that's happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so you would... you... like... that's another good point.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you expect to find the pain of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: On the same level as the objects are, you expect to see some kind of direct confirmation, observable, palpable confirmation, that this thing is not painful, that this thing is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't find it there, because it's found at the place of that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, a subha practice, for example, could be very easily done.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the level of that, like looking at more objects, like unpleasant objects, to prove yourself that the pleasant objects are not worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're still operating on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's to be seen on that foundation for you to see that whether the objects are pleasant or not, this foundation remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually, you basically, you don't get rid of the objects, but it ceases to matter
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when it doesn't depend on you having to manage, basically, having to... Because all we were saying, like, if a person still tries to do it on the level of objects, it can be turned into the same thing, like, okay, sensuality is painful, sensuality is suffering, but if it's not seen,
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, as a background to the pleasure, but it's attempted to be seen as a foreground again, then it won't really work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might kind of, to some extent, give you motivation to not act out, but as soon as the motivation to kind of apply that
[SPEAKER_00]: That observation onto the foreground runs out, then you're back onto the pleasure, because it basically depended on manipulating the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that leads us to kind of what I was going to ask before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would a person... what would be a very practical way for a person not to fall
[SPEAKER_00]: Into denial of the contents, like trying to see the suffering, trying to see the impermanence on that kind of management level, so that it's... that perception sets in at the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which perception?
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception that sensuality is suffering, that these things are not satisfactory, that they lead to harm, that they're unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would a person have to do for that to be applied on the right level, not on the level of the objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is it that makes you
[SPEAKER_00]: Not applied on the right level, let's say that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, are you asking what makes someone fall away from that origin?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or not find it in the first place, let's say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or not find it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like they're preoccupied with a certain goal that automatically means that they will be, whatever they do, won't be at the level of the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, what needs to be understood is that that origin is more fundamental than your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is that a bit of a jump?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because a person might, like, at that point, if this is not abandoned, anything that a person is thinking about on the level of sense of self is still going to be imagined.
[SPEAKER_03]: I see.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so we are one step back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe to consider or think whether what you're aiming towards, however it is out there, so to say, kind of relating to what you were saying before, is that this level of thing already there, or this, what you call it, fundamental, is not something you have to create or find, so to say,
[SPEAKER_01]: But why would you be trying to create something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you think what's here is not optimal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it not optimal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because it's felt in a way which I don't like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it's because you want to get rid of the displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what way a person is thinking about it, they might have the most accurate understanding of that origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that motivation behind them trying to discern us is still on the level of trying to get rid of what the objects are doing, like the pressure that the pleasant objects are exerting in this case, if that automatic endeavor or primal endeavor to
[SPEAKER_00]: escape that that this pleasure is not is not given up, then, whatever they do will just be trying to manipulate the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, even if they're trying to see, oh, this is unpleasant, in the case of neutrality, this is ultimately suffering, this is impermanent, all of it will be just another, basically, object.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be... it won't be the background to this, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in order for it to be a background, you need to have two things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're trying to replace the first thing, how can you have the background?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're just trying to have one thing in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to have... you don't realize it, of course, but in the end, you're not trying to see the pleasure as pain, which requires you to have the pleasure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to have pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, or the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, could be the other way around as well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, on the one hand, one needs to leave everything, including the pleasure and pain of objects, which is that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a sense, one needs to let it be as it is and not interfere, while simultaneously discerning the background to it, keeping one's intentions in mind that one is not now discerning that origin, hoping to bring about a change in that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how letting it be, what is a more accurate way of saying that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because a person, again, you might be telling yourself, I have to let it be, I have to let it be, because you don't want to let it be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you have to endure the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you can't be telling yourself anything, I'm gonna let it be, I'm gonna let it be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, the pressure is kind of the thing that's pointing you to do all of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might, oh, I'm gonna, I'm gonna...
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a reason by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, a person needs to accept that the origin is for the sake of...
[SPEAKER_00]: The discernment of the origin happens when you endure the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of... that's how you... that's how you're seeing the background to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see the background to that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the background to something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a good example of this, actually, is the practice of metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, often it's done as a form of trying to
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say somebody upsets you or something, and you want to... instead of training yourself so that the pressure of an unpleasant situation doesn't become ill-will, you try to make yourself have affection for the person, so that the situation is not pressuring anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not actually training the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like saying, you know, you have a... you're not used to the cold, but then, instead of exposing yourself to the cold, so that it stops, you know, giving you all sorts of, whatever, hyperthermia or something, you just
[SPEAKER_00]: Your response is to go back into warmth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's not actually training the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the training of the mind happens when, while having the pressure, you keep the perspective that prevents that pressure from becoming sensuality, desire, aversion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the... yeah, that's what makes it be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about replacing the object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you want to, like, basically train your mind so that whatever object comes up, it's not disturbed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that's how you build up strength, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not by hiding from things to, kind of, wrestle against or, you know, exercise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, you need to expose your body to exercise to build up strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the thing is, a person might not be... well, they might never have been told that that's the direction where development happens, but at the same time, they might not be aware of themselves doing it, because that impulse to outrun the pressure is so primal and so deeply rooted, that you might have even heard, well, I shouldn't try to get rid of the pressure, and you're still doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it requires constant revision of
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you were saying before, the intention behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: The intention, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that is also how there's going to be the development of wisdom that takes place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say, well, that could be another way of describing what we were just saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's not going to be any fundamental insight or shift in one's whole relationship to the world, so to speak, if this is not done rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the insight is about the things that pressure you, not about something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: The insights usually that come up in meditation for people, it's on the basis of
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely just running away from the place where the pressure comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a different world, almost.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's actually, you know, fundamentally what matters to person, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: To be free from pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because... To be not moved by pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because that's kind of the human... that's a human world.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're gonna encounter when you get up the cushion and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Start talking to people is this pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not going to be encountering, you know, particles of nāmarūpa or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to be encountering pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: But you see, nobody actually wants to experience that pressure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the fundamental lack of wisdom is that one casually assumes that by acting out,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why then does it feel so natural to act out?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, actually, one doesn't want to have the pressure of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, that is why one acts out.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what is not seen is that the acting out
[SPEAKER_03]: means that basically your own mind has become the victim of that habit and so it becomes stronger.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the actual way out is to not act out and learn to strengthen the mind so that it is no longer pressured by those same things.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the recognition that one was acting out, because one didn't want to have it in the first place, is important to realize, so that it is not like, you know, like, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, because actually, you did not really want to have that pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so there is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But this is often not understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a catch-22.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a catch-22.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure becomes stronger because you want to get rid of the pressure, and the pressure becomes stronger, then you want to get rid of it more, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and it just keeps going round and round and round, actually making the situation worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's one another point to make.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your practice revolves around getting rid of the pressure, many times what will happen is that things that
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, it didn't bother you before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, it becomes bothersome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you weren't bothered by the sound of traffic, let's say, before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, when, like, on account of some kind of practice that's about running away from... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...every pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this thing is unsettling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, you're... the
[SPEAKER_00]: Requirements for your mind to be at peace become more and more strict.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that is sort of a sensitivity, but in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it becomes... What I'm saying is, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you try to run away from pressure, the more it's going to bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: With that sort of practice, you can imagine, if
[SPEAKER_00]: That is bothering you so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: What will happen when, you know, you go back to the same intensity of life that you had before?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you might have toned it down because of your practice and you don't experience the same breadth and intensity of things anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to go back, if you had to abandon your
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, like, if a person is clear about this, that it's about enduring the pressure, then
[SPEAKER_00]: There's like any practice you do within that, it's going to be right for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your endurance of the pressure is correct, whether you're doing the four satipaṭṭhānas, whether you're doing metta, whether you're doing a subha, to the extent to which you can enjoy the pressure is the extent to which
[SPEAKER_00]: Your practice has the right basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's also where you can start to discern what is wholesome and what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because many times, unwholesome things can be ways of... what is ordinarily thought of as wholesome, can be rooted in just trying to get rid of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like being, again, like I said now, loving-kindness, which is the usual interpretation of metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems wholesome, very wholesome on the surface, but if you ask yourself, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because the pressure that's there now, kind of the starting point that I had,
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is the ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how can you practice loving-kindness when your starting point is that you are not free from ill-will?
[SPEAKER_03]: Towards your own experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a complete contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, that's what would be determining things as wholesome and unwholesome in the most ultimate sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue, for example, you can take on a thousand precepts, but if all of it is based on trying to outrun the pressure that comes from doubt, like, if I don't have every single aspect of my day meticulously planned beforehand, I'm going to experience the pressure of doubt and uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even though, on the surface, all these observances are wholesome, they might be very austere, very ascetic, but if it's done for the sake of running away from the pressure, then, ultimately, it can't be pushing the mind to wish freedom from craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Have you clarified sufficiently about this yoniso, manasikāra, and how to practically go about it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or should we say something more about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, maybe that's something worth mentioning, or we should have started maybe with it, even that these are these two factors which are
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's so important to actually ponder about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess that's one good thing to mention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could summarize yonison manasikāra as saying that it's attention that
[SPEAKER_00]: Attention that endures the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, on the basis of that, when you heard the utterance of another, about the nature of that pressure, eh... why it's unsatisfactory to... eh... unbeneficial to act out of it, why it's not in your control, why it arises on its own, all of that can become recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now, you are not
[SPEAKER_00]: Because acting out of the pressure means trying to own it, automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you have the utterance of another, of the suttas, they're telling you that nothing... nothing is... nothing can be owned, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could summarize the entire Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you're acting out of pressure, you are at... you're very trying to get rid of the pressure, is saying
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, like, that pressure has something to do with me.
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, the acting out...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so then, you might have perfect knowledge of the suttas, but... and you're applying the same teaching on the surface.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're applying the perception of anicca, dukkha and anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, all of it is done because you want to get rid of the pressure, means all of it is done on the basis of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can't give rise to the right view, because it's not... you're not getting to understand that ultimate direction of relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all still being done on the basis of what I want, basically, just to get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and that is putting yourself first, basically, in your attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that origin of attention, which is where
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling, vedanā, cannot go, basically, second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, you are still the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you are still the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, actually, the whole point of practicing yoniso, manasikāra, is seeing that your whole experience, including what you take yourself to be, is second from that origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, perhaps, we should also say that
[SPEAKER_03]: When we're talking about the source or the origin, that there's absolutely nothing theistic about that, because here in the West, you know, the whole history of religious and philosophical thought centers around the question, you know, whether God exists or not, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we are not saying that
[SPEAKER_03]: God is the source of all values and that this is what we have to find in our experience somehow.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, it might be easy for people to fall into that mistake.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is a...
[SPEAKER_03]: There's nothing theistic about anything that we've said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and not only in the sense of theistic, but also in just a general mystical sense that this source is somehow something that you can find
[SPEAKER_00]: safety in and that it's yourself or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't have to be an explicit formulation of it as, okay, this is God or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, it's important to recognize that it's just, you could say, a structural principle that whenever something arises in your experience,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's going to be something else that is a foundation for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you turn your attention to that which is a foundation now, then something else will be the foundation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else will be the source.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you do the same thing and it happens again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, none of those things are...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no such thing as a fixed source, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It all depends on what are you directing your attention towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you engaged in right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that as well, the source is the foundation for what you're attending to, but there would be no source if there would be no background, if there were nothing that you were attending to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means that that source is also impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It also depends simultaneously
[SPEAKER_00]: On what you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we can go, for example, in the case of sensuality, we're talking about these sensual objects and sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can say, well, your body, your feeling, any of these things the Buddha talks about, you can see it as the source.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there were no central object there, no experience there right now, how could you talk about something that is the foundation for it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you talk about these other
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, they cannot stand on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these two directions that we started out with, mutually depend on one another.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another important thing to realize.
[SPEAKER_03]: In essence, why, when there is going to be the Noble Right View, the main principle that is being discerned is with this.
[SPEAKER_03]: This.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is... and... and this... and, you know, this two-fold attention is the exemplification which, when that is understood, you... that will be recognized on other levels as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not even necessarily recognized on all levels, but the principle is seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this then becomes the
[SPEAKER_03]: The noble method of the Eightfold Path, contemplating that principle and applying
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever it is that you're attending to there, recognizing simultaneously with it, that background.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, being in the suttas, can be a great joy, because the Buddha already basically points out, oh, when this is the foreground, that has got to be the background.
[SPEAKER_03]: When this is the foreground, that's got to be the background.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in a sense, you can just read that, and it's like, ah!
[SPEAKER_03]: And, and so, that's very helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's, that's what I was saying just now, with the practice of the subha, practice of metta, all these things that are usually
[SPEAKER_00]: That sometimes works, sometimes don't for people.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your discernment is on the level of that source correctly, it can't not work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it can't not give the result that it has to give.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't, it's because you're making a mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the... yeah, like you said, it's helpful, because then there's no way for you to go astray.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is only one way to go straight, which was not enduring the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's not just... like the right view as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just having yonison manasikāra, because, like I said, to some extent, anyone can have that source or develop it more than others.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: yonison manasikāra as yonison manasikāra and understanding ayonison manasikāra as ayonison manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognize, you could say, recognizing in yourself when you're enduring the pressure and when you're trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing that clearly means you will always know what is wholesome and what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is beneficial, what is unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what how Majjhima Nikaya 2 starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says the ending of
[SPEAKER_00]: of the influxes is for the one who knows these two things, yoniso manasikāra and ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the person who can tell whether what they're reading from the suttas, they're doing it rightly, meaning yoniso, or wrongly, ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.